<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: Code School | eval everything]]></title>
  <link href="http://evaleverything.com/tags/code-school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://evaleverything.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-04T16:07:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://evaleverything.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Adam Fortuna]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching iOS 7 at Code School]]></title>
    <link href="http://evaleverything.com/2013/10/04/teaching-ios-7-at-codeschool/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-04T14:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://evaleverything.com/2013/10/04/teaching-ios-7-at-codeschool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A long time ago, at a <a href="http://adamfortuna.com/wwdc/">WWDC</a> far away, 3 travelers from <a href="http://codeschool.com">Code School</a> journeyed to Apple Mecca in search of new technologies. The goal was to see what was new in iOS 7, while looking for ways to best teach this new addition to the iOS world.</p>

<p>This week we released the result of that experience.</p>

<h2>Think Outside the Browser</h2>

<p>Up to this point, every Code School course has used an in browser editor. This simple interaction makes sense for learning a new topic from scratch. You don&rsquo;t need to install anything on your local system, and you can see what it&rsquo;s like to develop in a sandbox. After you&rsquo;ve learned the ropes, you want a taste of programming in the real world. <a href="https://twitter.com/eallam">Eric Allam</a> thought there could be a better way to pull this off.</p>

<p><div class='pull-left '><p><img src="/images/codeschool/core-ios-7.png" alt="Core iOS 7" class="icon" /></p>
</div></p>

<p><a href="http://ios7.codeschool.com">Core iOS 7</a> goes a different path. After watching a video on a topic, you&rsquo;ll be prompted to download a zip file. Unzip this file and you&rsquo;ll have an entire Xcode project, with a unique identifier in it that Code School uses to identify you. In this project you complete a series of tasks, then run the tests in Xcode. The results of which are sent to the course, and you see the results in your browser.</p>

<p>The easiest way to see how this all fits together is the 10 second video Eric created for the <a href="http://blog.codeschool.com/post/62915764253/introducing-core-ios-7">Code School Blog</a>.</p>

<p><div class='pull-right '><p>For a more elaborate take on this course, check out the Erics post on the <a href="http://blog.codeschool.com/post/62915764253/introducing-core-ios-7">Code School Blog</a>.</p>
</div></p>

<p></p>

<iframe src="http://evaleverything.com//player.vimeo.com/video/75897272" width="100%" height="350" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p></p>

<p>Did you see that? We use <a href="/2013/09/08/native-javascript-notifications/">native browser notifications</a> and <a href="/2013/09/07/response-streams-with-rails-4-and-redis/">response streams</a> to push the latest results back immediately.</p>

<p>Native editing using the same tool you&rsquo;d use, coupled with an interactive course with videos makes for a more direct connection between you and the code. The course prompts you with tasks to complete in Xcode, you perform them, run the test suite, and the site is updated to reflect what tasks are left to complete. The result of this is that you&rsquo;ll see feedback in the browser immediately following a test run from Xcode.</p>

<h2>Videos in Context</h2>

<p><div class='pull-right '><p>You probably should just watch everything he’s ever done.</p>
</div></p>

<p>Recently <a href="http://worrydream.com/">Bret Victor</a> put out an inspiring, interactive version of his last talk, <a href="http://worrydream.com/MediaForThinkingTheUnthinkable/">Media for the Unthinkable</a>. This presentation of the content hit close to home. Ever since <a href="http://railsforzombies.com">Rails for Zombies</a>, Code School&rsquo;s courses have featured videos, followed by in browser challenges. The only way to see the video was to navigate back to it, view the video, and then go back to the challenge. We&rsquo;ve long known we could do better, but this format was the kick we needed at the right time.</p>

<p>In the footer of interactive version of his <strong>Media for the Unthinkable</strong> talk, Bret goes into the thought behind this method of displaying the content:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>But a talk is a poor knowledge-container. It&rsquo;s opaque. The viewer can&rsquo;t skim, browse, or get a gist at a glance. Ideas can&rsquo;t be looked up as needed; they feel fleeting. The medium works well for entertainment — watch and enjoy — but not for a toolbox.</p><footer><small>Media for the Unthinkable <a href="http://worrydream.com/MediaForThinkingTheUnthinkable/">http://worrydream.com/MediaForThinkingTheUnthinkable/</a></small></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><div class='pull-right '><p>Videos are a toolbox.</p>
</div></p>

<p>Our videos are a toolbox. You pull one out and use to solve the challenges that come after, so why would you want to navigate away to rewatch one? Putting them in context only made sense. Each task you are prompted to complete has an associated position within the video you previously watched which you can call up with a click, at the moment you need it.</p>

<h2>iOS Education</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/eallam">Eric Allam</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/jonfriskics">Jon Friskics</a> did an amazing job on the content for this course, while <a href="http://justinmezzell.com/">Justin Mezzell</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/dandenney">Dan Denney</a> created an vivid design. I worked exclusively on the Rails/JavaScript side which presented some extremely exciting challenges to solve &mdash; and served as the content for the first few posts on this blog. I don&rsquo;t know what the future of iOS education will be, but I&rsquo;d like to think we&rsquo;re pushing the boundries and continuing to improve.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Native Notifications with JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://evaleverything.com/2013/09/08/native-javascript-notifications/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-08T23:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://evaleverything.com/2013/09/08/native-javascript-notifications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In browser notifications have made a lot of progress in the last few years. Hell, native notifications have made a lot of progress in that time too. Just a few years ago, everyone on the Mac was using <a href="http://growl.info/">Growl</a>. With the release of Mac OS X 10.8 (Mountain Lion) the one purpose of Growl was now built in and everyone I know made the switch to using native notifications.</p>

<p><div class='pull-right '><p>Warning: Link to the official spec.</p>
</div></p>

<p>Notifications caught on with Mac App developers. <a href="http://notifications.spec.whatwg.org/">HTML 5 Notifications</a> have had a slower growth curve as the various browsers focus in on a single standard. As of this writing, here&rsquo;s a recap of where the different browsers stand when it comes to supporting notifications.</p>

<p>OS X Mavericks has expanded support for notifications that builds heavily on this. Here&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s public on the topic so far:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Once users have signed up for notifications from your website in Safari, you can send them push notifications that appear just like app notifications, even when Safari isn’t running. Users can then click on your push notification to launch your website.</p><footer><small>OS X Mavericks for Developers <a href="https://developer.apple.com/osx/whats-new/">https://developer.apple.com/osx/whats-new/</a></small></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>In other words, it&rsquo;s time to hop on board the notification train if you want another route of reaching your sites visitors. Let&rsquo;s check out how this applies to the different browsers.</p>

<h2>Common Traits</h2>

<p><div class='pull-right raw '><p>Read the source from this project to understand how browsers implement notifications</p>
</div></p>

<p>The major browsers (setting aside IE) have a few patterns in common right now that we can use to style our behavior pattern around. If you want see how to use notifications in different browsers, check out the <a href="https://github.com/ttsvetko/HTML5-Desktop-Notifications/">HTML5 Desktop Notifications</a> project on GitHub. It&rsquo;s worth reading over the source code.</p>

<h2>Request Permission</h2>

<p>In order to send notifications in all browsers, you&rsquo;ll need to request permission to do so. In that very long spec, there are 3 permission levels noted:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>default</code> &ndash; No permission granted or denied</li>
<li><code>granted</code> &ndash; The user has granted permission to send notifications</li>
<li><code>denied</code> &ndash; The user has denied permission</li>
</ul>


<p>If permission is denied you won&rsquo;t be able to request permission again in the current session. If you try to send a notification without having been granted permission, nothing will happen.</p>

<h2>Send A Message</h2>

<p>Once you have permission, you&rsquo;ll be able send down a notification with the following attributes:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>title</code> &ndash; Should be short and to the point</li>
<li><code>body</code> &ndash; You&rsquo;ll have a bit more room to work with here. Unfortunately, in Safari this will be truncated</li>
<li><code>icon</code> &ndash; In Chrome and Firefox, you can send over whatever icon you want. This isn&rsquo;t being served by Notification Center, so there is more flexibility here.</li>
</ul>


<p>When the message is shown, there are also a few events that we can tie into for added flexibility:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>onshow</code> &ndash; When the notification is first shown.</li>
<li><code>onclick</code> &ndash;  When the user clicks on the notification. By default this will bring the window into focus.</li>
<li><code>onclose</code> &ndash; When the notification is closed, either by the user or programatically.</li>
<li><code>onerror</code> &ndash; Trigger if the notification cannot be presented to the user</li>
</ul>


<p>Here&rsquo;s a few examples of how these notifications look in different browsers.</p>

<p><div class='pull-left '><p><img src="/images/icons/safari.png" alt="Safari" class="icon" /></p>
</div></p>

<h3>Safari</h3>

<p>For Safari notifications, you won&rsquo;t be able to provide an icon unfortunately. Instead it&rsquo;ll always use the Safari icon. It will also show the hostname where the notification came from though, which is unique to Safari.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/native-javascript-notifications/safari-notification-small.png" alt="Safari Notification" /></p>

<p>One of the nice parts of this notification is that it will sync up with your other notifications. For instance, if you have one notification from Xcode and another from a website, they&rsquo;ll show up stacked rather than on top of each other.</p>

<h3>Mavericks</h3>

<p>Not exactly a JavaScript implementation, but worth noting that notifications in Mavericks behave much differently than HTML 5 notifications. They more closely resemble iOS notifications, where you&rsquo;re pushing to Apple&rsquo;s servers, and they&rsquo;re pushing to the end user.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/native-javascript-notifications/mavericks-notification-small.png" alt="Mavericks Notification" /></p>

<p>The addition of a custom icon here is definitely a plus. This alert is from a <a href="http://kandutech.net/">Safari Push Notification Demo</a> which should only work if you&rsquo;re running Safari in Mavericks. If you clicked on that alert, you&rsquo;d get taken to a page that describes how it works:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>When you allowed this website to send you push notifications, we generated a 4 digit code and put it in a database along with your Mac&rsquo;s push token. When a push notification is triggered through our servers, we resolve the 4 digit code to your Mac&rsquo;s token. Once we have your token, we tell Apple&rsquo;s servers what the notification should look like, and where it should go. Apple&rsquo;s push notification service then delivers the notification we generated to your Mac.</p><footer><small>Safari Push Notification Demo <a href="http://kandutech.net/clicked">http://kandutech.net/clicked</a></small></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><div class='pull-left '><p><img src="/images/icons/chrome.png" alt="Chrome" class="icon" /></p>
</div></p>

<h3>Chrome</h3>

<p>Chrome notifications show up square, which stands out from the rounded look of OS X and Firefox notifications. It also shows up larger in all dimensions</p>

<p><div class='pull-right '><p>Chromes notifications are significantly larger than Notification Center.</p>
</div></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/native-javascript-notifications/chrome-notification-small.png" alt="Chrome Notification" /></p>

<p>Unlike Safari notifications, this will stay up until it is dismissed.</p>

<p><div class='pull-left '><p><img src="/images/icons/firefox.png" alt="Firefox" class="icon" /></p>
</div></p>

<h3>Firefox</h3>

<p>The Firefox notification would be prettiest out of the box, but the entire body is shown as a link! For all notifications, clicking on it takes you to the page, but Firefox attempts to make it more apparent. The appearance ends up suffering due to this choice.</p>

<p><div class='pull-right '><p>Why is the body a link Firefox? WHY?</p>
</div></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/native-javascript-notifications/firefox-notification-small.png" alt="Firefox Notification" /></p>

<p><div class='pull-left '><p><img src="/images/icons/ie.png" alt="Chrome" class="icon" /></p>
</div></p>

<h3>Windows</h3>

<p>While there are no system level notifications in Windows (I don&rsquo;t think?), but Internet Explorer 9 and up allow you to add an icon overlay on the browsers icon. This allows for some feedback in this browser. You can see an example of this in the Readme for the <a href="https://github.com/ttsvetko/HTML5-Desktop-Notifications/">HTML5 Desktop Notifications</a> project on GitHub.</p>

<p>Chrome and Firefox on Windows support notifications that behave similar to their Mac counterparts.</p>

<h2>Demo</h2>

<p>Want to see how notifications look in your browser? Try out the <a href="http://ttsvetko.github.io/HTML5-Desktop-Notifications/">HTML5 Notifications Demo</a> to find out.</p>

<h2>Update</h2>

<p>For an example of how this technique is used, read the post on <a href="/2013/10/04/teaching-ios-7-at-codeschool/">Teaching iOS 7 at Code School</a>. This post details the user experience that can be achieved using native browser notifications.</p>

<p><div class='credits'><h2>Credits</h2><ol>
  <li>Icons for Safari, Chrome and Firefox by <a href="http://dribbble.com/shots/1032875-Flat-Icons">Stefano Tirloni</a>.</li>
  <li>Internet Explorer Icon by <a href="http://onelittledesigner.com/rapidweaver/web-icons/free-flat-browser-icons/">1 Little Designer</a>.</li>
</ol>
</div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Response Streams with Rails 4 and Redis]]></title>
    <link href="http://evaleverything.com/2013/09/07/response-streams-with-rails-4-and-redis/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-07T18:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://evaleverything.com/2013/09/07/response-streams-with-rails-4-and-redis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;re on the fence about updating an older application to use Rails 4, the addition of <code>ActionController::Live</code> might be helpful in making your decision a little easier. It enables keeping a connection open to your server, which can then respond with partial updates with ease. This bridges one of the bigger gaps that causes people to choose <a href="http://nodejs.org/">node.js</a> over Rails for projects.</p>

<h2>A Basic Redis Connection</h2>

<p><div class='pull-right '><p>If you’re looking for an intro, read Aarons post.</p>
</div></p>

<p>Aaron Patterson wrote a great post about <a href="http://tenderlovemaking.com/2012/07/30/is-it-live.html">Live Streaming in Rails</a>, over a year ago, but the interface is mostly the same today. That post is still a good starting point for <code>ActionController::Live</code>.</p>

<p>I first ran into the subject when working on Code School&rsquo;s <a href="http://rails4.codeschool.com/">Rails 4: Zombie Outlaws</a> course where the last level is all about streaming, with a mention towards the end about using it in cooperation with Redis. The example we show in that</p>

<p><div class='pull-left code '><p>If you connected to this endpoint in a browser, it’d load forever and occasionally send back responses to the browser</p>
</div></p>

<p>```ruby
class ActivitiesController &lt; ApplicationController
  include ActionController::Live</p>

<p>  def index</p>

<pre><code>response.headers["Content-Type"] = "text/event-stream"
redis = Redis.new

redis.psubscribe("user-#{current_user.id}:*") do |on|
  on.pmessage do |subscription, event, data|
    response.stream.write "data: #{data}\n\n"
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  rescue IOError</p>

<pre><code># Client disconnected
</code></pre>

<p>  ensure</p>

<pre><code>redis.quit
response.stream.close
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a quick recap of what&rsquo;s going on:</p>

<ul>
<li>We&rsquo;re using <a href="https://github.com/puma/puma">Puma</a> which allows for concurrent connections to the server.</li>
<li>We create a new connection to Redis. This is important because when we call <code>psubscribe</code>, that connection is locked, and can&rsquo;t do anything else.</li>
<li>Use <code>psubscribe</code> to subscribe to all messages for this user by using an expression. Elsewhere in the application, we are <code>publish</code>ing messages to this same channel.</li>
<li>When a message is received, it&rsquo;s passed down to the client. In this case we&rsquo;re passing down JSON.</li>
<li><code>ensure</code> that the <code>redis</code> connection is <code>quit</code> and the response is ended.</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p>If you wrote the above code and opened up that action in a browser, it would actually work fine &mdash; until you tried to load the page again. At that point there would be two connections open from the servers standpoint, but only one active. This is due to the fact that the server doesn&rsquo;t know that the client disconnected.</p>

<p><div class='pull-right code '><p>Good discussion at github/rails on this issue</p>
</div></p>

<p>That <code>IOError</code> error isn&rsquo;t triggered when the client disconnects as you might expect, but instead when the server attempts to write to the <code>response.stream</code> only to find that it is no longer active. Turns out this is a <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/issues/10989">well discussed problem</a> That leaves us with a few options on how to test if the client has disconnected:</p>

<ul>
<li>Have the server connection timeout every minute or so. (If you&rsquo;re on Heroku, my guess is this will automatically happen)</li>
<li>Ping the client every few seconds to see if they are still there.</li>
</ul>


<h2>A Working Solution</h2>

<p>I ran into a <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/14268690/actioncontrollerlive-is-it-possible-to-check-if-connection-is-still-alive">StackOverflow</a> post on this exact topic, which lead to <em>a</em> working solution for this.</p>

<p><div class='pull-left code '><p>This solution follows the “ping” method.</p>
</div></p>

<p>```ruby
class ActivitiesController &lt; ApplicationController
  include ActionController::Live</p>

<p>  def index</p>

<pre><code>response.headers["Content-Type"] = "text/event-stream"
redis = Redis.new

ticker = Thread.new { loop { sse.write 0; sleep 5 } }
sender = Thread.new do  
  redis.psubscribe("user-#{current_user.id}:*") do |on|
    on.pmessage do |subscription, event, data|
      response.stream.write "data: #{data}\n\n"
    end
  end
end
ticker.join
sender.join
</code></pre>

<p>  rescue IOError</p>

<pre><code># Client disconnected
</code></pre>

<p>  ensure</p>

<pre><code>Thread.kill(ticker) if ticker
Thread.kill(sender) if sender
redis.quit
response.stream.close
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>This solution is based on the idea that the server will know the client has disconnected when it attempts to write to it only to find it&rsquo;s now there. In this case we open up two threads &mdash; one that does our Redis subscription, and another that handles making sure the client is still there.</p>

<p>If you know of a better way of doing this, I&rsquo;d love to hear it. Short of using Sinatra, Goliath or another middleware this is the only way I&rsquo;ve found to handle this.</p>

<h2>Closing the Database</h2>

<p>One downside of keeping the connection open is that if you&rsquo;re using ActiveRecord, that connection will not be released until the request is complete. During the Redis subscribe phase, if you don&rsquo;t need to keep that connection open, you can return the current connection to the <code>connection_pool</code>.</p>

<p><code>ruby
ActiveRecord::Base.connection_pool.release_connection
</code></p>

<p>If you set this up to run in a <code>before</code> filter, and do any database communication before that, you shouldn&rsquo;t run into database connection limits.</p>

<h2>Update</h2>

<p>For an example of how this technique is used, read the post on <a href="/2013/10/04/teaching-ios-7-at-codeschool/">Teaching iOS 7 at Code School</a>. This post details the user experience that can be achieved using response streams.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
